Guide to the Papers of David Thoreau Wieck and Diva Agnostinelli TAM 227
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Thoreau Wieck and Diva Agnostinelli Papers
1913-1996
1943-1994
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 227
7.75 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize folder.
David Thoreau Wieck was the son of Agnes Burns Wieck who wrote for the Illinois Miner and worked as an organizer for the Progressive Miners of America. Moving to New York, Wieck graduated from Columbia University and was briefly a member of the Young Communist League (circa 1935-36), but became more sympathetic to anarchism. In July 1943, he began serving a three-year sentence for being a conscientious objector. After his release, he received a Ph.D. in philosophy from Columbia University. He began teaching philosophy at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in 1960 and retired as Professor Emeritus in 1987. During his tenure he published numerous articles and was the author of a biography of his mother, Woman from Spillertown: A Memoir of Agnes Burns Wieck (Southern Illinois Press, 1992). Wieck died on July 1, 1997. These papers include some of his correspondence, clippings, memorabilia, journals (1986-93), manuscripts and notes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials open without restriction with the exception of ten folders of restricted correspondence in Box 7. Materials are restricted until 2020.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance unknown but the collection was likely donated by Diva Agnostinelli in 1998. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1998.006, 1998.007, and NPA.2000.287.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Biography, undated
Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1996
Series III: Diaries and Journals, 1932-1993
Series IV: Writings, 1916-1993
Series V: Graphics and Photographs, 1934-1992
Series VI: Unprocessed Material, 1952-2007.
Material is arranged alphabetically, with the exception of Series III which is arranged chronologically and Series VI which has not been arranged by an archivist.
Historical/Biographical Note
David Thoreau Wieck was born in St. Louis, Missouri on December 13, 1921. Named after David Henry Thoreau, he was the son of Edward A. and Agnes Burns Wieck. His mother, known as the Mother Jones of Illinois, was the daughter of a miner. She was a writer in the middle and late 1920s for the weekly journal Illinois Miner, and after training with the Women's Trade Union League, she worked as an organizer for the Progressive Miners of America. His father was a self-educated coal miner and writer. In 1934 the Wiecks moved to New York City when Edward Wieck was hired as a research associate for the Russell Sage Foundation's Industrial Studies Department. David Wieck joined the Young Communist League in 1935, but by 1936 had become, in his own words, a "dissident bolshevik," much more enamored of the anarcho-syndicalists then fighting in Spain.
He enrolled at Columbia University in 1937 and graduated in 1941. He subsequently did post-graduate work toward a masters degree with Leo Wolman, writing an unpublished study of the process of centralization in the United Mine Workers of America. Registering as a conscientious objector following the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, he left New York City in early 1943 pending his appeal and was arrested in New Orleans for not notifying his draft board of his "change of address." In July 1943 Wieck began serving a three-year sentence at the Federal Correctional Institution in Danbury, Connecticut for refusing induction into the United States Armed Services. As prisoner #2674 Wieck was involved in numerous actions protesting racial segregation in the federal prison system.
He was released from prison in 1946 and began a life-long marriage/life-partnership with Diva Agostinelli, herself the daughter of an anarchist coal miner from Pennsylvania. In the late 1940s and early 1950s Wieck wrote for the anarchist publications Why?, Liberation, and Resistance. He enrolled again at Columbia University in 1956 and received a Ph.D. in Philosophy in 1961, apparently concentrating on aesthetics. He began teaching philosophy at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in 1960, retiring as Professor Emeritus in 1987. During his tenure he published numerous articles and reviews in professional journals and the radical press both in the United States and abroad. He was the author of a biography of his mother, Woman from Spillertown: A Memoir of Agnes Burns Wieck (Southern Illinois Press, 1992). Afflicted with Alzheimers Disease, Wieck died on July 1, 1997.
Related Material
The Swarthmore College Peace Collection holds the bulk of Wieck's Danbury prison correspondence (Collection CDG-A., David Thoreau Wieck). Wayne State University's Walter P. Reuther Library holds the papers of Wieck's parents, Edward A. and Agnes Wieck.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains clippings, memorabilia, correspondence, writings and other personal materials. The bulk of the correspondence dates from between 1965 and 1992, although some letters sent to Wieck during his incarceration at Danbury Federal Correctional Institution are included here. Wieck's writings are well-represented in this collection, including his diaries and journals, as well as notes, drafts, reviews and manuscripts of published and unpublished works. These writings include drafts for the "Woman from Spillertown," "Comic as an Aesthetic Concept," "The United Mineworkers of America: A Study in Centralization," and Wieck's Masters thesis and PhD dissertation. The writings and correspondence of Wieck's parents, Agnes Burns Wieck and Edward Wieck, and his life-partner Diva Agostinelli are also included. There are a small number of photographs of Wieck's family and friends, as well as drawings produced by Wieck and others.
Drawings (visual works); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Graphic arts; Conscientious objectors |z United States.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Typescripts.; Diaries; Anarchists |z United States.; Bookchin, Murray, 1921-2006; Dellinger, David T., 1915-2004; Baldelli, Giovanni; Avrich, Paul; Bennett, Clif; Benello, C. George; Cantine, Holley R.; Deutsch, Eliot; Koven, David; Labadie, Laurance, 1896-1975; DeWees, Daniel; Goodfriend, Audrey; Mac Low, Jackson; Naeve, Lowell; Lind, Ian; Lind, Meda; Stoehr, Taylor, 1931-; Stone, Ralph W. (Ralph Walter), 1876-1964; Perry, Ruth, 1943-; Rainer, Dachine; Wieck, David Thoreau, 1921-; Williams, Paul.; Williams, Vera; Agostinelli, Diva, 1921-2007
- Series I: Biography, undated
  - Biography, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal, undated (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1996
  - Adams, Frank, Margaret, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agostinelli, Diva, 1953-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agostinelli, Diva, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Avrich, Paul, 1974-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baldelli, Benvenuto, Giavanna, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baldelli, Giovanni, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baldelli, Giovanni, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baldelli, Giovanni, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baldelli, Patricia, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benello, George, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bennett, Clif, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bookchin, Murray/ New England Anarchist Conferences, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Burns, Kevin, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Burns, Patrick, Lois, 1962-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Calese, Bob (Robert S.), 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cantine, Holley and Rainer, Dachine, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clark, John, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Coughlin, Michael E., 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Danbury letters, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Danbury letters: Chaim Sklover, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - D'Attilio, Bob/ Black Rose, 1972-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Deutsch, Eliot, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Deutsch, Eliot, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Deutsch, Eliot, 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Deutsch, Eliot, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - DeWeeds, Daniel, 1964-1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Editrice A / Finzi, Paolo, Aurora, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Efron, Arthur, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Einarsson, Peter, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Feldman, Irving, 1965-1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ferguson, Kathy, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31a)
  - Free Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Freedom Press/ Raven/ Richards, Vernon (Vero)/ Ward, Colin, 1958-1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Friends of Malatesta/ Convocations Board/ Dickens, Bob, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gartner, Dan, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Goodfriend, Audrey, 1961-1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Grant, Alma, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Grudin, Betty, Arnold, 1971-1992 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hallon, Bob, Dorothy, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hunt, Nancy/ Sangamon University, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Jackson, T.R., 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Joughlin, Louis, Jean, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Koven, David, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 42a)
  - Koven, David, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 42b)
  - Koven, David, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 42c)
  - Koven, David, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Koven, David, undated (Box 1, Folder 42e)
  - Labadie, Laurance, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Laslett, John H. M., 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Liberation/ Dellinger, Dave, 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Lind, Meda and Ian, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Lind, Meda and Ian, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lind, Meda and Ian, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Linden, Lou and Yolanda, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Mac Low, Jackson, 1961-1995 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mayer, Ada and Hank, 1971-1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1975 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Naeve, Lowell, Virginia, 1959-1977 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Naeve, Lowell, Virginia, 1980-1994 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Naeve, Lowell, Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Nelson, Juanita, Wally, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 59a)
  - Norwood, Stephen, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Owens, Juanita, 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 60a)
  - Peck, Jim, 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Porter, David, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Publishers, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Publishers relating to Woman from Spillertown, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Rasmussen, Paul/ Order of the Blade and the Whet-Stone, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Series III: Diaries and Journals, 1932-1993
  - Diary, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Diary, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Diary, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Diary, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Journal, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Journal, 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Journal, 1972-1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Journal, Aug 1986-Dec 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Diary, Jan 1987-Apr 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Diary, May 1987-Aug 1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Diary, Sep 1987-Dec 1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Diary, Jan 1988-Apr 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Diary, May 1988-Aug 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Diary, Sep 1988-Dec 1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Diary, Dec 1988-Jul 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Diary, Jul 1991-Oct 1992 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Diary, Oct 1992-Oct 1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Series IV: Writings, 1916-1993
  - Subseries A: Philosophy Notes.
    - Philosophy Notes, Nov 1956-Jan 1957 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Philosophy Notes, Feb 1957-Mar 1957 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Philosophy Notes, Sep 1957 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Philosophy Notes, Dec 1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jul 1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jul 1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Philosophy Notes, Feb 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Philosophy Notes, Sep 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Philosophy Notes, May 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jul 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jan 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Philosophy Notes, May 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jul 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Philosophy Notes, Aug 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Philosophy Notes, Sep 1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Philosophy Notes, Nov 1962-Feb 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Philosophy Notes, Dec 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Philosophy Notes, Mar 1963-May 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Philosophy Notes, May 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Philosophy Notes, Sep 1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Philosophy Notes, Oct 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Philosophy Notes, May 1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Philosophy Notes, Jun 1964-Jul 1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Philosophy Notes, Nov 1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Philosophy Notes, Sep 1965-Dec 1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Philosophy Notes, Aug 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Philosophy Notes, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Philosophy Notes, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Philosophy Notes, Dec 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Philosophy Notes, 1960-1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Philosophy Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Philosophy Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Philosophy Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Philosophy Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Subseries B: Other Philosophical Writings.
    - "Aesthetic Inquiry", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Aesthetics", undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Aesthetics Manuscript: part 1, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Aesthetics Manuscript: part 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Aesthetics Manuscript: part 3, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Aesthetics Manuscript: part 4, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Aesthetics Manuscript: part 5, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "A Notebook without Order", undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Aphorisms, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Comic as an Aesthetic Concept: Chapters, I, II, and II (Doctoral Dissertation), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Comic as an Aesthetic Concept: Chapters IV, V, and VI, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Comic as an Aesthetic Concept: Chapters VII, VIII, IX, Bibliography, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Draft Material: "Funny Things" and "Comic as an Aesthetic Concept" (I), undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Draft Material: "Funny Things" and "Comic as an Aesthetic Concept" (II), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Funny Things" (I), undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Funny Things" (II), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Manuscripts", undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Musings on Rexroth and circle, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes on Croce; chapter on "Intuition and Expression" from the Aesthetic, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Paris Is a Work of Art", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Odds and Ends," notes, etc., undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Scribblz-work" Part 1 [diary 1978], undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Scribblz-work" Part 2 [diary 1978], undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Scribblz-work", 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sexuality, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Relevance of Psychoanalysis to Aesthetics: a Critical Discussion of Some Psychoanalytic Hypothesis on Art (Masters Thesis), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Vision", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries C: Woman from Spillertown.
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Woman from Spillertown, Nov 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Woman from Spillertown, Apr 1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Woman from Spillertown: Prologue, Chapters I and II, Feb 13, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Woman from Spillertown, Chapters III and IV, Feb 13, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Woman from Spillertown, Chapters V, VI, VII, Feb 13, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Reviews, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Subseries D: The United Mineworkers of America: A Study in Centralization (unpublished typescript).
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters I, II, III, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters IV, V, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters VI, VII, VIII, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters IX, X, XI, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters XII, XIII, XIV, XV, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters XVI, XVII, XVIII, XIX, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - The United Mine Workers of America: A Study in Centralization: Chapters XX, Chapter 7A, Bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - UMWA, Part 1 of 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - UMWA, Part 2 of 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - UMWA, Part 3 of 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "The Miners' Union", undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Subseries E: Miscellaneous Writings.
    - Anarchism: notes and bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "An Introduction to a Biography; Being a Pretext for an History, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - "Beyond Annihilation", undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - "Classless Society and the Stateless Society" Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - "Early Utopias", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "European Syndicalism", undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "European Syndicalism", May 1941 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - "Goodman's Flag", 1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "Houses: The House We Live In" and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - JAAC Reviews, 1962-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Moral Responsibilities of Scientists and Scholars", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Musings", undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes on Nestor Makhno, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Old miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - On Paul Goodman, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "Playing Games", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Published Essays and Letters, 1951-1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Recent notes, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "Remembrance of Giovanni Baldelli", 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Science and Reality", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Serious Essays", undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - "Some Thoughts on Cooperation", undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Somewhat on the Knowledge of Good and Evil", 1958 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "S.E. Asia-Vietnam (WRL Policy, Vietnam, Howe, et al.)", undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Strange Anarchy": Review of Film "Anarchism in America", undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Taoism/Anarchism", 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "The Anthracite Mine Strike of 1900 and 1902", undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - "The Farm", undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "The Irrelevance of Intellectuals, or the Madness of a Nation", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "The Quest for Liberty", undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - "Theses of Anarchism", undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "Thoreau" [notes for biography], undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Untitled [possible course on anarchism], undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "Visions", undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - On Max Stirner: part 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - On Max Stirner: part 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Subseries F: Writings by Others.
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Why Anarchism", undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Menzogne Revoluzionarie e Liberazione Sociale", undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Man, Woman, and Death" part 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Man, Woman, and Death" part 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Man, Woman, and Death" part 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Passion Is Brief" Poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "EMP of the Cloudings", undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Not Revolution but Liberation" Vol. One, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Not Revolution but Liberation" Vol. Two, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "Not Revolution but Liberation", undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: front, back covers: "Not Revolution but Liberation", "Man, Woman, and Death", "Menzogne Revoluzionarie e Liberazione Sociale", "Why Anarchism", undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: "The Positivity of Anarchism", undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Giovanni Baldelli: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Eliot Deutsch: "The End" (a one act play), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Emma Goldman: on Peter Kropotkin, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Emma Goldman: Letter on Violence and Anarchism, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Paul Goodman: "Faustina", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Jackson Mac Low: Poetry, 1943-1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - John Moore: Prophets of the New World; Noam Chomsky, Murray Bookchin and Fredy Perlman, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Sal Restivo: "Science, Sociology of Science, and the Anarchist Tradition", 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - John Schumacher: Conversations between John A. Schumacher and Cedric O. Evans, Jul 1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - John Schumacher: "Can We (Only) Reason in an Armchair?", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - John Schumacher: "The Sound of Silence", undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - John Schumacher: "Our Responsibility for the Future in Higher Education", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - John Schumacher: "Popular Epidemiology, Local Knowledge, and Human Posture", undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - John Schumacher: "The Posture of Persons", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Subseries G: Agnes Burns Wieck.
    - Biography, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Amelia Burns, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: John Walker, 1916-1918 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - District 12 Address, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Condemned uv God", undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Subseries H: Edward Wieck.
    - Correspondence: Gerry Allard, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: John Walker, 1917-1919 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence (some letters signed or co-signed by Agnes Wieck): Hapgood Family, 1922-1932 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Journal: "Six Months on the Pit Committee" (UMW Grievance Committee), Oct 22, 1923-Jan 20, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Journal: "Six Months on the Pit Committee" (UMW Grievance Committee), Jan 21, 1924-May 9, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Series V: Graphics and Photographs, 1934-1992
  - Artwork I, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Artwork II, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Artwork III, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Burns Family: Photographs, 1991-1992, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, undated (Box XOS003, Folder 1, Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Grudin Family: Portrait, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Koven, David: Portrait, circa 1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Naeve, Lowell: Drawings, 1989, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Faculty: Portrait, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - United Mine Workers of America, 37th Constitutional Convention (Cincinnati, Ohio), 1942 (Box XOS003, Folder 1)
  - Wieck, David Thoreau: Portrait, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Wieck, [Edward?]: Mines and Miners in Alabama and Tennessee, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Broadside: Agnes Burns Wieck lecture, "The Need for Labor Schools", undated (Box Shared Tamiment 011, Folder 13)
- Series VI: Unprocessed Material, 1952-2007
  - Diva Agostinelli: Writings and Correspondence, 1952-2007 (Box 8)
    Scope and Content Note
    Contains poetry, personal and political writing, and correspondence with David Thoreau Wieck and others.